اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝
بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله رَبِّ الْعَلَمِيْنَ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد
وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْراً
اَلسَّلَامُ عَلَيْكُمْ وَرَحْمَةُ الله
This is beginning of our second week In Sha Allah Ta'ala(إن شاءالله تعالى)
on the series of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه.
On Friday we were talking about
some of the freedoms that were granted by the Khalifah(خليفه).
We move on to the freedom of property or Hurriyyat-Tamalluk(حريةالتملك)
but in English we would call it, Property Rights.
It's more of right then freedom(of property), it's rights.
And the Khilafah(خلافة) granted the Muslims  property rights
and not only that but sometimes, it would give out, hand out to the citizens, property.
Such was the case with Rasool Allah ﷺ who gave Bilal Ibn Rabah رضي الله عنه a large piece of land,
very large piece of land.
Now, since the population was expanding,
and the size of the Khilafah(خلافة) was expanding and number of Muslims was going up,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه, he went to Bilal Ibn Rabah(بلال ابن رباح), and he told him,
Rasool Allah ﷺ has given you a large piece of land and you are unable to cultivate it all,
it was either pasture land or it was agricultural land,
and Bilal(بلال) wasn't able to invest all of that land, so part of the land was still wasted.
So Bilal Ibn Rabah(بلال ابن رباح) said: "Yes".
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: Then, I want you to hand me over, the land, which you are not cultivating.
Bilal(بلال) responded and said: "I am not gonna give you something that was given to me by Rasool Allah ﷺ,
No way! I am going to give you this land back.!
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: "Yes you will"!
And he took away from him the part that was not cultivated and he distributed it, among the Muslims.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) did not want people to hold up these pieces of land,
when they could be given to other Muslims, who will cultivate them.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) wanted the benefit of the whole.
While Bilal Ibn Rabah(بلال ابن رباح) was looking at it that,
this was the piece of land that was given to me by Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, anyway, he took it away, and distributed it to the Muslims.
So, the point to learn here is that "property needs to be invested."
it needs to be cultivated and not just left like that.
and this shows you the interest that the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) had in promoting trade and commerce.
FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION AND SPEAKING.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) is the Khalifah(خليفه) and he meets a man, who just came out of a court.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) use to judge
in the time of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب), he was a Qadhi(قاضي).
So this man came out and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) told him;
What was the ruling of Ali(علي) and Zayd(زيد)?
" So, the man said: "so and so."
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: "If it was me, I would have ruled otherwise".
So, the man said: "What prevents you from doing so, if you are the Ameer(امير) of the Believers?"
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: "If this was an issue that straight goes to the book of Allah
or the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ I would enforce my ruling
but this is my opinion and my opinion is as good as opinion of Zayd(زيد) and Ali(علي)."
So, he went along with the ruling of Zayd(زيد) and Ali Ibn Abi Talibرضي الله عنهما,
even though it is contrary to what he thinks, is the right ruling,
and that shows you the freedom of expression that existed in the time of Khalifah(خليفه)
he didn’t enforce his opinion on Ali Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنه and Zayd(زيد).
He was once giving Khutba(خطبه) and he told the Muslims,
If you see any crookedness in me, then I want you to fix it, to make it straight.
So a man stood up and he said: If we see any crookedness in you, we will straighten it with our swords".
This was the very outspoken member of the society.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب), did he call in, his security guards and say,
this is terrorism against the state and this man must be thrown in jail,
and we need to keep him away, he is harm to society?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: "Alhamdulillah(الحمد لله)! Praise be to Allah!
Who has made in the Muslims someone, who will fix Umar(عمر), with his sword, if umar(عمر) goes wrong.
Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدلله)! That Allah has granted me followers, that will straighten me up if I go wrong."
Umar(عُمَر) was happy, Umar(عُمَر) was happy that, this was the state of Ummah(امة) at that time.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) wasn’t looking for submissive followers,
who would say this is Wali Al-Amr(ولى الامر), we'll just do, whatever he wants,
he can take away our wealth, and lash, flog our backs and we will just say,
سمعناواطعنا
We listen and obey!
He could do right, we will follow him, he could do wrong we will follow him, we are just blind followers.
No, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) wanted to make sure that, this wasn't the condition of the Ummah(امة).
He wanted to make sure that the Ummah(امة) are only going to follow him, if he is right
and they will stand up and correct him, if he is wrong.
And he was very happy when he saw that, somebody willing to use force to do that.
Obviously this is something that Ummah(امة) needs to learn today.
Because the Ummah(امة) have became blind followers, submissive and they have given into to Zulm(ظلم).
They have accepted Zulm(ظلم) on themselves and others.
And they have accepted this state of humiliation that the Ummah(امة) is going through.
The Ummah(امة) needs to stand up and fight for its rights.
If you don’t fight for it, you're not going to get it,
Amazing condition of the society.! Once he was giving the khutba(خطبة)
and he said: Is'mioo(اسمعو) Wa' Ati'oo(وأطيعو). Listen and Obey!
One man stood and said: We are not going to listen and we are not going to obey.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: "why?
He said: Because, you have given us each, one piece of cloth and I see you wearing two pieces.
This was some pieces of fabric that came into Madina,
he gave it out and he gave everybody one piece.
And now, this man is seeing Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) is wearing two pieces,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: "Call Abdullah(عبدالله)", his son Abdullah(عبدالله).
Umar(عُمَر) said: "I am not going to answer this, Abdullah(عبدالله) will".
So, he calls in his son Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله بن عمر) and he tells him;
"Tell them, how come I am wearing two pieces of cloth?"
Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله بن عمر) said;
لَئَنَّ أَبِيْ رَجُلٌ طَوِيْلَ الْقَامَةْ العَرِيْضَ الْمُنْكَبَيْنْ
My father is a very tall man, with wide shoulders,
so one piece of cloth is not enough for him, so I gave him mine.
I gave him mine.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) did not take an additional piece from the Muslim Treasury.
This shows you, how delicate the justice of Umar(عُمَر) was,
and it shows you how delicate the standard of the Muslims was.
They did not even accept for the Khalifah(خليفه) to have an additional piece of cloth, that they don't have.
Very, very, very different standards than we have now.
Some Muslims are even willing to be owned by the king or president.
They see it as a rightful claim for the government to just take away your wealth,
abuse the wealth of the Ummah(امة).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) another time was talking, giving a Khutba(خطبه)
and he was angry that the Mahr(مهر) was going up.
Mahr(مهر) is the dowry and Umar(عُمَر) wanted the dowry to be reasonable
and he was quite upset that the prices were going up.
So, he gives a Khutba(خطبه) and says the Mahr(مهر) should not go above this amount
and if I hear that any Mahr(مهر) is over this amount,
I am going to take the additional amount and put it in the treasury.
So, a woman stood up and old woman stood up and said:
"It's not up to you to do that."
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: "Why?"
She said: because Allahعَزّوجَلّ says:
وَآتَيْتُمْ اِحْدَاهُنَّ قِنْطَارَا
It mentions in Qur’an that "You give the woman a Qintaar(قنطار)"
Allahعَزّوجَلّ was referring to some issues of marriage
and it mentions in the Ayah(آية) and Qintaar(قنطار) is a large amount of Gold.
So, this woman used this as a Daleel(دليل) as an evidence that you can give Mahr(مهر) as much as a Qintaar(قنطار).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: "A man was wrong and a woman was right."
In another narrations, it says:
أَصَابَتْ اِمْرَأَةْ وَأَخْطَاءْ عُمر
A woman was right and Umar(عُمَر) was wrong.
In a third narration, it says; that he said:
كُلُّ اَحَدْ اَفْقَهْ مِنْ عمر
"Everyone has more Fiqh(فقه) than me".
And these are the examples to show the, also not just the justice,
but it also shows the humbleness of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب), you know
for somebody to stand up and just correct him in public, his pride didn’t take over, he accepted it.
and he said, everybody has more Fiqh(فقه) than me.
There are exception to this rule Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) just didn’t give a blanket freedom of expression
to anyone and everyone to say whatever they want.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) placed restrictions just like we saw, he place restriction on property rights,
he also placed restrictions on freedom of expression.
He was, once giving a Khutba(خطبه), and in the beginning of the Khutba(خطبه),
he make the opening of the Khutba(خطبه), and it says:
مَنْ يَهْدِالله فَلَا مُضِّلَّ لَهْ، وَمَنْ يُضْلِلِ لله فَلَا هَادِيَ لَهْ
Whomever, Allah guides nobody can misguide him and whoever, Allah misguides nobody can guide him.
So, this man stands up and Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم), if he was Muslim or not, any way he said;
Allahعَزّوجَلّ does not misguide anyone, because it says;
وَمَنْ يُضْلِلِ لله فَلَا هَادِيَ لَهْ
And whoever Allah misguides, nobody can guide him.
So, now he is bringing up a controversial issue in Qadar(قَدَر).
And Qadar(قَدَر), Dear brothers and sisters is one area where we should belief,
we should not try to delve into and try to comprehend,
it's one area that should be taken as Eeman(ايمان) in Al-Ghaeb(الغيب).
Belief in the unseen.
Why?
Because some aspects of Qadar(قَدَر) are beyond human comprehension.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ has taught us the knowledge that we need to know, He didn’t teach us everything.
Allah taught us in Qur’an things that we need to know.
There are some things that, there are many aspects of knowledge that are not mentioned in the Qur'an
because we don’t need them, we don't need them for Hidaya(هداية).
So for example in Surat-Ul-Kahf(سورة الكهف).
Some were debating, and this was mentioned in some of the books.
They were debating on the Issue of the Dog.
You know the dog of the people of the cave.
People of the cave, they had a dog and this dog is mentioned in the Qur'an,
وَكَلْبُهُمْ بَاسِطٌ ذِرَاعَيْهِ بِالْوَصِيدِ ۚ
So, they were debating, what color is this dog?
Is it black or white or is it black and white or is it red or yellow.?
What's the benefit of such knowledge?
What will you gain by knowing the color of the dog? NOTHING.!
عِلْم لَا يَنْفَعْ
This is knowledge that does not benefit.
Therefore, it wasn’t mentioned to us.
You find that Qur’an does not mention the details of time, of names, of locations,
you would have entire story and no location would be mentioned, no time would be mentioned.
In some stories you would have a time line, some stories you would have locations but its for a benefit.
But these details are left out there is clear difference
when you read a story in the Bible and when you read a story in Qur’an
it could be the same story but they are very different.
The Bible gets into the name of the man, and his wife, and their fathers, and their relatives and their tribes
and who did this and who did that!
But the Qur’an goes straight into the story and mentions to you the just of it Al-Ibra(العبرة).
لَقَدْ كَانَ فِيْ قَصَصِهِمْ عِبْرَةْ
"In those stories are reminders", benefits.
So, issues that are irrelevant are not mentioned in the Qur’an because this Qur’an is the Book of Guidance.
You are not going to find chemistry in Qur’an, you are not going to find physics in Qur’an, Why?
Because these are the issues that are not really important for our guidance.
Qur’an has mentioned every single thing we need to know in order to we get into Jannah(جنة)
and save ourselves from hellfire, all that is mentioned in the Qur’an.
So, the issue of Qadar(قَدَر) we know of Qadar(قَدَر) what we need to know
- but there are some parts of Qadar(قَدَر) we don’t need to know,
so we are not told about them and our minds cannot comprehend them.
So, this man is talking about How can Allah misguide us? Allah does not misguide.!
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told him; "If you ever say that again, I am going to execute you".
You know Umar(عُمَر) does not play around, I am going to execute you.
He goes straight to the point and he knows how to deliver the medicine.
In another example, there is, this man who is within the Muslim army a soldier Fi Sabeel-Lillah(في سبيل الله) fighting
and then he will go around, you know, because in camps you have a lot of free time
you are not fighting all the time, there is time of Ribaat(رباط)
when people are waiting and you are guarding your outpost.
So, the Mujahid(مجاهد), who knows his benefit would use that time to learn,
to study Shari’ah(شريعة), to make Ibaadah(عبادة), you know like Al-Murabitoon(المرابطون)
there was this great Islamic Emarat(عمارة) in the North Africa in our history, called Al-Murabitoon(المرابطون).
These were scholars and their students, who would set base
in the frontier between the Muslim land and the non Muslim land.
And they would fight Fi Sabeel-Lillah(في سبيل الله) to spread the religion
and when they are not fighting they are studying.
The Shoyukh(شيوخ) are teaching them the ‘ilm(علم).
So, there time was spent in fighting Fi Sabeel-Lillah(في سبيل الله), Ribaat(رباط), Daw'ah(دعوة) and ‘ilm(علم).
The best things that you could ask for.!!
However, there was this man Yani(يعني) in the time of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), this man was in the army.
He would go around asking about the Ayaat(آيات) Al-Mutashabihaat(المتشابهات)
the Ayaat(آيات) that the meaning is not clear.
There are some Ayah(آية) in Qur'an, That are Muh'kam(محكم) and some Ayah(آية) are Mutashabiha(متشابهة).
The Muh'kam(محكم) is very clear, the meaning is direct.
And there is Mutashabiha(متشابهة), it is unknown and it takes time for the Ta'aweel(تعويل) to be known
with the some Ayaat(آيات) the final Ta'aweel(تعويل) will only be known on the day of Judgment.
So, this man was going around and he would say,
What does (وَالذَّارِيَاتِ ذَرْوًا) - Mean?
what does, (الْحَمِلَاتِ وُقْرَا) mean?
فَالْجَارِيَاتِ يُسْرَا
And he goes around these soldiers and asking them these controversial questions.
And nobody has an answer and he was causing so much gossip.
So, the Ameer(امير) of the army was quiet concerned
because you know, we have a lot of new Muslims and why raise these issues?
And some people are up to not that level of knowledge.
So, you don’t talk about everything.!
So, he came to the Ameer(امير) and said I have these questions for you, what does this mean, what does this mean...?
So, the Ameer(امير) of the army, he sends a letter to Umar(عُمَر) and telling him about this situation.
Umar(عُمَر) said: Sends him to me, bring him over.
So, they send this guy down to Umar Ibn Khattab(عمرإبن خطاب)
Umar Ibn Khattab(عمرإبن خطاب) wraps him, in a rug.
And then he celts that rug and then he starts beating him
with a stick and he had some of the Sahabah(صحابه) joined him.
Actually before that, No! we go back.
The man comes in and Umar(عمر) meets him, and he says:
How can I help you?
The man said: I want to know what does - (والذاريات ذروا) mean?
And what does, - (فالحملات وقرا) - mean?
And Umar(عُمَر) is telling him go on, go on, go on!!!
And he is getting all these questions from him, he said: "I will give you all the answer".
So, he wraps him up into this rug and then he beats him up so bad,
and then Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: "You understand now?"
He said: "Yes Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين), I do! I know the answer! I know the answer now".
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: I never want you to ask these questions again.
They said, he left and he behaved himself until Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) died
and then he starting to asking the questions again.
Umar(عُمَر) was the one, who would stand between the Ummah(امة) and Fitnah(فِتْنَه),
He was the wall that stood between the Ummah(امة) and the Fitnah(فِتْنَه).
So, Islam does give freedom of expression but it does not allow to fool around with the religion.
It’s a serious issue the religion of Allahعَزّوجَلّ is serious.
He wouldn’t also allow to slander.
Al-Hatiyya(الحطيه) and Arab poet, his poetry was slandering others.
He was a wonderful poet but he use to slander other people.
So, one of the target of his slander came to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and complained.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) brought Al-Hatiyya(الحطيه) and threw him in jail.
Al-Hatiyya(الحطيه) made some poetry,
talking about his daughters and how Umar(عُمَر) has left them without care taker, now and very sad line of poetry.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) released him until, he had him pay three thousand Dinar(دينار)
as a compensation to those, whom he slandered and he said, you never slander again.
So, he prevented him, from slandering others.
And this is a serious problem in free societies today,
or so called free societies today for example in the west
that freedom of expression over spills, and it turns into slandering people.
I mean the media now, had a free hand in slandering people.
Look at how the Muslims are been slandered left and right.
And you can’t do anything about it.
Who you are going to sue, who you are going to hold accountable? It's just flood gates are open.
But Islam does not allow that, it doesn’t allow anybody to be slandered, it protects the dignity of the people.
HOW THE KHALIFAH(خليفه) LIVE?
You know some people have an impression as long as you are doing something for Islam,
you should do it Fi-Sabeel-Lillah(في سبيل الله) and don’t get paid for it, but that’s impracticable.
Somebody going to give all his time for the religion of Allahعَزّوجَلّ they need to make a living.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه told the Sahabah(صحابه), how much you are going to pay me?
And there is a Qa’ida(قاعدة) of Fiqh(فقه) it says;
اِنَّ كُلَّ مَحْبُوْسِ لِمَنْفَعَةْ غَيْرِهِ تَلْزَمَه’ نَفَقَتَه’
"Anybody who is dedicated for a cause that cause need to pay their expenses."
This is a the rule of Fiqh(فقه) and they give examples for that the judge,
like the Mufti(مفتى), and the Waali(والى)
Waali(والى) is the governor, Mufti(مفتي) is the scholar, and the judge.
Since, they have dedicated their time for a certain cause that cause need to pay their expenses.
With Rasool Allah ﷺ his expenses were paid through the Fai(فيئ),
the spoils of the war that are gained without fighting.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
جُعِلَ رِزْقِيْ تَحْتَ ظِلْ رُمْحِيْ
"My Rizq(رزق) comes from beneath my spear."
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ contrary to common misconceptions, wasn’t a businessman, after he became a Prophet?
He stopped practicing business and went Daw'ah(دعوة) full time.
Business and shepherding were things of the past.
After Rasool Allah ﷺ became a Nabi(نَبِي), he stopped working in any profession
and all what he would do is devote his time to the Daw'ah(دعوة) Fi-Sabeel-Lillah(في سبيل الله).
In Madina a new door of Rizq(رزق) opened up to Rasool Allah ﷺ and that is
the Ghaneema(غنيمه) or the Fai(فيئ).
When Rasool Allah ﷺ would send an army and no fighting would occur
that Fai(فيئ) would go into the hands of Rasool Allah ﷺ and he claims a portion of it.
Now, since that is specific to Rasool Allah ﷺ
the one who took the responsibility of the affairs of the Muslims after him, was Abu Bakr(ابو بكر).
Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) is not Rasool Allah ﷺ to take the Fai(فيئ), so how can he live?
We talked about this, during the lecture series on Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) but just briefly
after Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) became Khalifah(خليفه), they saw him in the market place buying and selling.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and Abu Obaidah(ابو عبيدة) told him what are you doing?
He said, what you mean what I am doing? I am making a living for me and my family.
They said, well there is some women waiting for you at your office
and you need to be working, you're the Khalifah(خليفه).
He said; I have to make a living, how am I going to feed myself and my family?
They said, alright we will give you a salary.
And they gave him half a sheep, a day and they also gave him a stipend some money.
And then later on they found Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) again in the market place, they told him what's wrong?
He told him, what you gave me is not enough.
So, they said, alright we will give you the whole sheep and will also raise your salary
and then he was satisfied and content.
Because Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) was a businessman he used to make sufficient money for him and his family.
So, at least his expenses need to be paid now.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he went to the Sahabah(صحابه) and he said:
What salary are you going to give me?
They said, well Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين) you know better.
He said; I'll tell you what I'll take, what I see as Halal(حلال) for me from the Treasury.
مَنْ أَحُجُّ وَأَعْتَمِرُوْ عَلَيْهِ مِنَّ الظَّهْرِيْ
"Transportation for my Hajj(حَجْ) and Umrah(عمرة)".
Since, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) is not gonna leave Madina, and he now doesn't need transportation in Madina.
So, he said, I want  transportation for Hajj(حَجْ) and Umrah(عمرة) otherwise, in Madina he is going to walk.
وَحُلَّتِيْ فِى الشِّتَآءِ وَالصَّيْفَ
"And set of clothes in summer and set of clothes in winter" just one set.
وَقُوْتُ عَيَالِيْ اُشْبِعُهُمْ
"And sufficient food for me and my family, I want them to be full."
وَسَهْمِيْ فِيءَ الْمُسْلِمِيْنَ
"And my share of the booty "
فَإِنَّمَا اَنَا رَجُلٌ مِّنَ الْمُسْلِمِيْنَ
"Because I am still a Muslim like you." I am one of you, so I want to get my share of the booty, As-Sahm(السهم).
That was the salary of Umar Ibn Al-Khattabرضي الله عنه.
Which is quiet modest.
A man came to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and said, this is an agreement between me and my brother,
that he borrowed some money from me, so he needs to pay me back
and he gives Umar(عُمَر) the agreement, and this man was saying that it's long overdue.
What does it say in the agreement, it says, that the debt should be paid back in Sha’ban(شعبان)
now the Arabs didn’t have a calendar.
They didn’t have a calendar to count the years, they had a calendar for months.
The twelve lunar months but they did not have a calendar for the years.
And the way Arabs would remember years is by the important event that happened that year
so you have Aamil Feil(عام الفيل) the Year of the Elephants.
Why was it call year of the Elephant?
Because that’s when Abraha(ابراهة) sent his army and it was destroyed.
You have ‘Aam ar-Ramada(عام الرمادة), the year of Famine
and you have Aam Al-Ghala(عام الغلاء), the year of Expensive Prices.
Because that was the important event that happened then.
But they didn’t have a numbering system for the years, they didn’t have a true calendar.
So, this man is telling Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) this money is long overdue.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) reads it and it said, Sha’ban(شعبان) he said, which Sha’ban(شعبان)?
This Sha’ban(شعبان), Sha’ban(شعبان) last year, Sha’ban(شعبان) next year?
So, he gathered the Sahabah(صحابه),
and now see things are getting more complicated because now we have a Khilfah(خلافه)
and it's expanding its not like family affairs like it was before and you could work things out.
And they did not have these sophisticated rules.
Now, you're having all these disputes happening.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said to the Sahabah(صحابه) we have to have a calendar.
And he was soliciting advice from them,
some said let's use the calendar of Romans, some said let's use the calendar of Persians,
some said let's use this and let's use that.
And then Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said;
مُنْذُوْ نُوْأَرِّخُ مُنْذُوْ أَنْ خَرَجَ النَّبِيْ مِنْ الاَرْضِ شِّرْكْ
Our calendar should start from the time Rasool Allah ﷺmade Hijrah(هجرة)
from the land of Shirk(شرك) to the land of Islam, the Hijrah(هجرة).
So, it's interesting to see that, the Sahabah(صحابه) did not use for example, the birth of Rasool Allah ﷺ
or his death or the date of his Prophet hood, they used Hijrah(هجرة).
Why Hijrah(هجرة)?
Why did they specifically choose Hijrah(هجرة), and didn’t choose his death or his birth.
Well for his death Ibn Hajar(ابن حجَر) says, because that would bring bad memories.
But then why didn’t they choose the date of his Prophet hood or the date of his birth?
Why did they specifically choose date of Hijrah(الهجرة)?
The Sahabah(صحابه) use to see the Hijrah(هجرة) is a turning point in Islam.
That is the beginning of Islamic State.
That is the beginning of living a Islamic life.
Before that we were a minority in Makkah.
But now, we have an Ummah(امة) a nation
and that’s why the Islamic Calendar should start from the Hijrah(هجرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, that’s the year but the month, Rasool Allah ﷺ made Hijrah(هجرة) in Rabia al-Awwal(ربيع الاول)
however, the Islamic calendar starts with which month?
What's the first month of the year?
Muharram(محرم),
Why did they choose Muharram(محرم)?
One of the opinion and this is the opinion of Ibn Hajar(ابن حجَر) is
because Muharram(محرم) was the beginning of the intention of Rasool Allah ﷺ to make Hijrah(هجرة).
Because Bai’at-Al-Aqabaa As-Saniya(بيعة العقبة الثانية), occurred in Zulhijah(ذوالحجة)
and the first Hilal(هلال) after Zulhijah(ذوالحجة), the next month after Zulhijjah(ذوتاحجة) is Muharram(محرم).
The other opinion is that it's good to start the year, after people come back from Hajj(حَجْ).
So, people come back from Hajj(حَجْ) in Zulhijah(ذوالحجة) make that, the last month of the year
and the people start off, the new year when they come back from Hajj(حَجْ).
It could make a sense, Hajj(حَجْ) forgives for you, your sins
and Umrah(عمرة) forgives the sins between Umrah(عمرة) and the next scenario starting again, in new month of Muharram(محرم).
So, that’s how the Islamic Calendar started,
it wasn’t something that was done in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ or the time of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر),
it was something that was started by Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
So, you can see that when Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
فَعَلَيْكُمْ بِسُنَّتِي وَسُنَّةِ الْخُلَفَاءِ الرَّاشِدِينَ الْمَهْدِيينَ، عَضُّوا عَلَيْهَا بِالنَّوَاجِذِ،
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: Follow my Sunnah(سنة) and the Sunnah(سنة) of the guided Caliphs after me.
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ knew that new affairs or circumstances would occur in the time of the Khulafah(خلافاء)
and there will be some new rulings given by the Khulafah(خلافاء) and that needs to be taken as Sunnah(سنة).
And many of these things occurred in the times of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه.
There was another dilemma what to name the Khalifah(خليفه), what name to give him?
With Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) he was given the name of,
What?
Khalifat(خليفة).
Khalifat(خليفة) who?
The successor of who?
Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Khalifatu Rasool Allah(خليفة الرسول الله), that was the title of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) ,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
You cannot call me Khalifah(خليفه) of Rasool Ullah,
I am not the Khalifah(خليفه) of Rasool Ullah, I am Khalifah(خليفه) of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
I am the successor of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر).
So, if you give me the name Khalifat Khalifah(خليفه) tu Rasool Ullah,
What about the ones who come after me?
It going to become very, very long.
Khalifat(خليفة), khalifat, khalifat ……. Rasool Ullah.
So, they were thinking about a title to give the Khalifah(خليفه) and they couldn’t come up with one?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: He wants two competent men come down from Iraq,
so that he can ask them about Iraq and its people.
He wants to hold a meeting with men from Iraq to ask them about the conditions in Iraq.
Iraq was a frontier land, there was a lot of fighting happening.
So, he wanted to know the latest news.
So, they brought him the Lubaid Bin Rabi’a(لبيد ابن ربيعه) and Oda’e Bin Hatim(عدي بن حاتم).
They came and they met Amro Bin Aas(عمرو بن العاص)
and they told Amro Bin Aas(عمرو بن العاص) can you please ask permission for us from Amir Ul Momineen(أميرالمؤمنين).
Amro Bin Aas(عمرو بن العاص) he went to Umar(عُمَر) and he said;
السلام و عليك يا امير المؤمنين
السلام وعليكم يا امير المؤمنين
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said, where did you get that from?
Amro Bin Aas(عمرو بن العاص) told him; Lubaid Bin Rabi’a(لبيد ابن ربيعه) and Oda’e Bin Hatim(عدي بن حاتم) are outside
and they said; we want permission to meet Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين)
and I liked that name because we are the believers and you are our Ameer(امير).
You are our Ameer(امير)!
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: "that would be the title"
and since then Khulafah(خلافاء) were given the title of Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين).
SOME OF THE QUALITIES OF AMEER UL-MOMINEEN(امير المؤمنين), Umar Ibn Al-Khattab Al Farooq رضي الله عنه,
He had such great fear of Allah in his heart,
he had Khashiya Allah(خشية الله) and that's the fruit of knowledge, Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
إِنَّمَا يَخْشَى اللَّهَ مِنْ عِبَادِهِ الْعُلَمَاءُ ۗ
"The ones, who have fear of Allah are the Ulema(علماء)",
so that’s the fruit of knowledge.
The name of one man was mentioned in front of Imam Ahmad Bin Hanbal(امام احمدبن حنبل), so some of his students said;
he is not a scholar.
You know, they were putting him down, he doesn’t have Ilm(علم).
Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) responded and said;
"He has the fruit of knowledge," the fear of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
He already has the fruit of knowledge that is actually what you want knowledge to do for you,
to have the fear of Allahعَزّوجَلّ and he had that.
Anyway, with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) he had the Khashiya(خشية) of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Once a man came to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب)
and he said, O Umar(عُمَر)! I want you to solve this dispute happening between me and this man.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) became upset and he said,
تَتْرُكُوْنَ عُمر وَهُوَ مُقْبِلٌ عَلَيْكُمْ حَتَّى اِذَاا شّتَغَلَ بِاَمُوْرِ الْمُسْلِمِيْنَ اَتَيْتُمُوْهَ
"When I come to you offering my help in my free time you don’t come forth
and when you see me busy with the affairs of the Muslims, you rush to me
and he hit him with his stick.
The Durra(درة), the famous stick of Umar(عمر)
this is very famous stick, this is called Ad-Durra(ألدرة), the Durra(درة) of Umar(عمر).
The man left and he was upset, he was complaining and he walked away.
Sometimes, it happens that when you are free nobody comes to you
and when all the paper work is piling up and you are so busy
everybody comes in with these urgent demands.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said; Call the man back.
So, they called him.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) gave him the stick and he said;
"I want you to hit me, like I hit you!"
The man said: "For the sake of Allah and for your sake I won’t".
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: "No".
You either do it, for the sake of Allah or you hit me back.
Then the man said: I will do it, for the sake of Allah alone.
Al-Ah'naf bin Qais(الاحنف بن قيس) said: "I was with Umar(عُمَر) when that happened.
And he went into his house and we went with him and then he prayed
and after he finished his Salah(صلاة), he said;
يَا اِبْنِ الُخَطَابْ! كُنْتَ وَضِيْعًا فَرَفَعَكَ الله، وَكُنْتَ ضَالًا فَهَدَاـكَ الله ،
وَكَنْتَ ذَلِيْلاً فَاعَزَّكَ الله،
ثُمَّ حَمَلَكَ عَلى رِقَابِ الْمُسْلِمِيْنَ فَجَاءَكَ رَجُلٌ يَسْتَعْدِيْكَ فَضَرَبْتَه،
مَاَ تَقُوْلُ لِرَبِّكَ غَدًا اِذَا اَتَيْتُه؟
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said, O son of Khattab(خطاب), he is speaking to himself!
He said: O son of Khattab(خطاب), You were low and Allah raised you,
you were lost and Allah guided you,
you were humble and Allah made you noble
and then Allah appoints you over the Muslims,
and a Muslim man comes to you asking for your help and you hit him.
How will you answer to Allah on the Day you meet Him?
What will you do and you will stand in front of Allahعَزّوجَلّ, how will you answer Allah for what you have done?
Al-Ah'naf bin Qais(الاحنف بن قيس) said: When I saw that I knew the Umar(عُمَر) was the best of the men.
This is the fear that he had, he regretted what he did with this man.
Even though he was busy Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) did not see that he had the legitimate reason for doing what he did.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) used to say;
حَاسِبُ اَنْفُسَكُمْ قَبْلَ اَنْ تُحَاسِبُ
"Hold yourselves accountable before you will be held accountable."
وَزِنُوْهَا قَبْلَ اَنْ تُوْزَنُوْا
"And weigh yourselves on the scale, before you would be weighed."
وَتَزَيَّنُوْا وَتَهَيَّئُوْ الِلْعَرْضِ الْأَكْبَرْ
"And prepare yourselves for the great exposition."
يَوْمَ تُعْرَضُوْنَ لَا تَخْفَى مِنْكُمْ خَافِيَةْ
"The day you will be exposed and nothing will be hidden, prepare for that time, prepare for that day."
Once Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) with his stick again, he hit men and women,
who were making Wudhu(وضؤ) in a pool next to Al-Ka’aba(الكعبة) in Al-Haram(الحرم).
So he hit them with his stick, he told them to go away.
And then he called one of his employees, so the employee came and said;
لَبَّيْكَ وَسَعْدَيْكََ
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب)" said: No lubayka(لبيك), No Sa’daiyka(سعديك)!"
Didn’t I tell you to make separate pools for men and separate pools for women?
Because they were making Wudhu(وضؤ) from the same pool
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) didn’t want that mixing to occur next to the House of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
So, he pushed them away.
And then he told his employee why didn’t you follow my instructions?
And then Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he went to Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) and he said:
هَلَكْت
"I perished!".
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said: "Why did you say that?"
He said: "I hit men and women in the House of Allah in the Haram(حرم)".
Ali Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنه said: "You are a shepherd
and if the shepherd disciplines his flock then that is justice
but if the shepherd disciplines his flock wrongly then that is oppression!"
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) is saying you are a shepherd and you have a right to discipline
your flock when you see them doing wrong.
Al-Hassan al-Basari(الحسن البصري) said, that one night while Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمربن الخطاب) was walking in the streets of Madina,
he remembered the Ayah(آية).
وَالَّذِيْنَ يُؤْذُوْنَ الْمُؤْمِنِيْنَ وَالْمُؤْمِنَاتْ
The one's who harm, the believing men and the believing women,
so he goes and visits Obaey Ibn Ka’aba(ابيئ ابن كعب),
Obaey Ibn Ka’aba(ابيئ ابن كعب) was a scholar of Qur’an.
He was one of the scribes, he was one of the memorizers of Book of Allah,
he was one of the Mufassireen(مفسرين), so Umar(عُمَر) visits him.
And as soon as he comes in to his house, Obaey Ibn Ka’aba(ابيئ ابن كعب) pulls down a pillow from beneath him
and his gives it to the Khalifah(خليفه).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) kicks the pillow away and he sits down on the floor.
And then he said: "Obaey(ابيئ) I fear that I am one of those, who are harming the believing men and the believing women."
Obaey Ibn Ka’aba رضي الله عنه told him.
لَا تَسْتَطِيْعَ إِلَّا اَنْ تُعَاهِدْ رَعَيَّتَكْ فَتَأْمُرْ وَتَنْهَى
O Umar(عُمَر)! You cannot but discipline your subjects and tell them what is right and what is wrong.
You have to do that, you are the Khalifah(خليفه), Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said:
قَدْ قُلْتَ وَاللهُ أَعْلَمْ،
You have consoled me or you have comforted me, that's not the right translation really,
"You have said the right thing, you have said the right thing"!
So Umar Ibn Khattab(عمرإبن خطاب) said: You said the right thing.
But this shows you that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه used to have fear of Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and he was so afraid that he would harm his subjects,
he would harm someone and then he would be held accountable for that on the Day of Judgment.
You know it's kind of difficult to make even a comparison between Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and some of the rulers of today.
Who are using every way, that you can possibly think off to abuse, their followers
and we are not talking about Kuffar(كفار) leaders, we are talking about the leaders in the Muslim world.
May be they are Murtadeen(مرتدين), anyway, so it doesn’t make any difference.
But I mean when you hear about their genius in the tools that they implement
to torture the Awliya(اولياء) Allahعَزّوجَلّ, as I might have mentioned before, they would rape their family members.
They would use homosexuals against them, they would use sorcery, magic,
they would actually hire magicians, hire sorcerers and fortune tellers, sorcerers and all different stuff,
to cast magic spells on these Awliya(اولياء) of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
They would use every psychological tool, that they could cast fear in their hearts, you name it.
Physical abuse everything.
These rulers, they never think about Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
they never think about the day, they will meet Allahعَزّوجَلّ and will be asked about what they're doing?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) sometimes when he would see fire, he would put his hand over it
he would put his hand in the fire and he would say; "O son of Khattab(خطاب)!
Can you have patience on this pain, is this a pain that you will be able to sustain? "
he is telling himself.
You need to be straight on Siraat-Ul-Mustaqeem(صراط المستقيم) when you are in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا)
because this will be the consequence in Akhirah(آخرة), if you are not.
And he would put his hand in fire and say; "Can you handle this? Son of Khattab(خطاب) can you handle this?".
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was outstanding in his Zuhd(زهد), in his austerity.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was seen giving Khuttbah(خطبه) in a Thowb(ثوب) that had twelve patches.
He was seen making Tawaf(طواف) in that thowb(ثوب).
A Khalifah(خليفه), and he has twelve, stitches in his thowb(ثوب)
and he wants to use it, until it's worn out completely before he gets a new one.
And he is the Khalifah(خليفه) of the Muslims.
Hafsa(حفصه) his daughter, the wife of Rasool Allah ﷺ  Umm-Al-Mo’mineen(ام المؤمنين) she came to him, and she said:
اِنَّ الله اَكْثَرَ الْخَيْرَ
وَ اَوْسَعَ عَلَيْكَ مِنَ الرِّزْقَ، فَلَوْأَكَلْتَ طَعَامًا أَطْيَبَ مِنْ ذَلِكْ وَلَبِسْتَ ثِيَابًاأَلْيَنَ مِنْ ثَوْبِكْ
She told him, Allahعَزّوجَلّ has provided us with a lot of blessings
and Allahعَزّوجَلّ has opened for us the doors of Rizq(رزق)
why don’t you get some better food and some better clothes?
During the times of Rasool Ullah, there was poverty, may be in the time of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) there was poverty,
but now we have Rizq(رزق) there is plenty.
Why are you still following those strict rules of the past?
Why don’t you have some better food and some better clothes?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) he looked at Hafsa(حفصه) and he said:
"I want you to be the judge."
And then he started reminding her with the way, Rasool Allah ﷺ used to live.
And he went on, and on mentioning examples to her until, Hafsa(حفصه) started to cry and then Umar(عُمَر) said;
"I have two companions, who preceded me and I am going to follow this way of hardship,
so that I can join them in the life of pleasure.
Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) they left before me and I want to follow them.
And I am going to follow this way of hardship, this life style of difficulty.
So, that I can join them in their life of happiness, this will be my way.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was not living for Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), he is living for the sake of
being reunited with his most beloved Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب), he was once walking with his companions,
advisors, deputies, came next to a dumpster, a garbage and he just stopped.
فَكَأَنَّ اَصْحَابَه’ تَأَاذَّ وْا بِهَا
"Until his companions were irritated because of the smell."
This was a horribly stinking dump and they were getting irritated
because he had them stand there for so long.
But Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was trying to teach them a lesson.
He said: This is your world, which you are fighting over and crying for.
This is Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), this is what you are fighting over, this is it, it’s a stinking dumpster.
And that is how Umar(عُمَر) saw this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), his interest was in Al-Akhirah(آخرة).
Sa’ad Bin Abi Waqas رضي الله عنه, he said;
وَاللهِ مَا كَانَ عُمر ابن الخطاب بِأَقْدَمِنَا هِجْرَةْ
"Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was not the earliest among us in Hijrah(هجرة)."
وَقَدْ عَرَفْتُ بِأَيِّ شَيْئٍ فَضَلَنَا
"But I know how come Umar(عُمَر) is ahead of us! I know how come Umar(عُمَر) is better than us."
كَانَأَازْهَدُنَا فِي الدُّنْيَاء
He was the most austere among us.
He was least attached to Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) among all of us.
That’s why Umar(عُمَر) stands above us, it is because of his Zuhd(زهد).
The Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) is right there in his hands and he leaves it, he discards it, he was very humble.
TAWADHIA(تواضع) OF UMAR IBN KHATTAB(عمر ابن الخطاب)
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was once approached by Al-Ahnaf Bin Qais(الاحنف بن قيس),
Al-Ahnaf Bin Qais(الاحنف بن قيس) is one of the leaders of his people.
A very dignified man, noble man he was respected by his community was loved and respected by Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he was a chief of a tribe.
So, he came and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب),
what was Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) doing?
The same thing he was doing when he was visited by Oyaiyna Bin Hassan(عيينه بن حصن) applying Tor to his camel.
Umar Ibn Khattab(عمرإبن خطاب) was applying Tor to his camel.
And this is difficult job to do and it is something that is done by the slaves.
You know, somebody who is well off he wouldn’t do that.
You are applying this Tor to the camel to clear it from the flees.
It's not something that should be done by somebody, who is a noble man let alone the Khalifah(خليفه).
But that’s what Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was doing.
And it's very difficult thing to do, so you have to take your clothes off.
So, Al-Ahnaf(الاحنف) came, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told him:
O Ahnaf(احنف) take your clothes off and come and join me.
Obviously when he said, take your clothes off, it means the outer garment,
you have your inner clothes that would cover your body on.
But your clean clothes that you wear when you outside take those out
because you are dealing with Tor, Qataraan(قطران).
So, there is one man with them he said: O Umar(عُمَر) Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين)!
Why don’t you have, a slave do that? Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) responded by saying;
وَأَيُّ عَبْدٍ هُوَّ أَعْبَدْ مِنِّيْ وَمِنَّ الْأحنف؟
"And who is more of a slave then me and Al-Ahnaf(الاحنف)?"
إِنَّه’ مَنْ وَلِيَ اَمْرُالْمُسْلِمِيْنَ، يَجِبْ عَلَيْهِ لَهُمْ مَا يَجِبُ عَلَى الْعَبْدِ لِسَيِّدِهْ فِيْ فِى النَّصِيْحَةْ وَأَدَاءِالْأَمَانَهْ
"And who is more of a slave then me and Al-Ahnaf(الاحنف)?
Anyone who assumes responsibility over the Muslims is accountable just like the slave is accountable to his master."
And he is talking about the fact that he is accountable to Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
He is a slave and Al-Ahnaf(الاحنف) is a slave and they are appointed over the Muslims,
so they need to be accountable to their Master, Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Just because I am your leader shouldn’t make you forget that I am still a slave
and that I have a Master above me, Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
In a gathering some man said,
مَا رَأَيْنَا رَجًلً أَقْضَى بِلْحَقِّ بِالْقِسْطِ
وَلَاأَاقْوَلَ لِلْحَقِّ وَلَاأَاشَّدَّ عَلَى الْمُنَافِقِيْنَ مِنْكَ يا امير المؤمنين
فَأَنْتَ خَيْرُا النَّاسِ بَعْدَ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
They said: We had never seen anyone, who is more just and who says, speaks the truth
and who is more severe on the Munafiqeen(منافقين) then you?
Auf Bin Malik(عوف بن مالك) who was sitting there he said: No! that's not true.
Kazabtu(كذبت), you are lying.
And then he said, we know of somebody, who came after Rasool Allah ﷺ who is better than Umar(عُمَر).
And this was said in front of Umar(عُمَر).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: "Who are you talking about?"
He said: "I am talking about Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)",
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: You are right.!
There was a time when Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابوبكر الصديق) was more pure then musk(مسك)
and I was more mislead then the camel of my parents.
I was in a worse condition then the camel of my family.
While Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه his smell was better than musk(مسك).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was saying that Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) became Muslim before me
and he was pure and clean like musk(مسك),
while I was a disbeliever and I was worse than the camel of my family.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) wasn't insulted by what this man said,
when he said that you are not the best after Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Umar(عُمَر) wanted the people to know who he really is?
And that he is in lower status than Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه.
He didn’t allow the people to tempt him, to believe that he is better
like people, the deceptive people do today to leaders.
They deceive the leaders and make them think that they are better than everybody else.
You are the best king that ever existed in history, you are the best leader that ever lived.
You are the best president, whatever!
And they pumped them up
and it gets to you, after a while it gets into your brains, and you really think that I am the best.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) did not allow that.
And he had, in his presence people, who would not allow that, like ‘Awf bin Malik(عوف بن مالك).
And HE WAS ALSO FOREBEARING:
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه even though he had that strong personality but he had Helm(حلم).
Oyaiyna Bin Hassan(عيينه بن حصن) again, his name comes up,
he is the Bedouin leader
whom Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) tore the document that was given by Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), he tore it apart.
Oyaiyna Bin Hassan(عيينه بن حصن) wanted permission to meet with Umar(عُمَر)
because Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would surround himself as Ibn Abbas(ابن عباس) says;
With the scholars of Qur’an.
These would be his advisors let's say.
They were friends and also advisors.
These are the people with whom he would surround himself with the Bataana(بطانه).
And Ibn Abbas(ابن عباس) said, it doesn’t matter whether they were old or young
as long as they were scholars in Qur’an they understood Qur’an they would accompany Umar(عُمَر).
So, one of them is Al-Hurr Bin Qais(الحر بن قيس).
Oyaiyna Bin Hassan(عيينه بن حصن) was his uncle.
So, Oyaiyna(عيينه) is coming to Al-Hurr(الحر) and said:
I want you to arrange a meeting between me and Umar(عُمَر), I want to meet him.
So, Al-Hurr Bin Qais(الحر بن قيس), because he is very close to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) he asked Umar(عُمَر)
for permission to have ‘Oyaiyna(عيينه) come in.
So, Umar(عُمَر) allowed him in.
Oyaiyna(عيينه) comes in and Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) look at what he said;
He said;
هِيْ يا ابن الخطاب فَوَالله مَا تُعْطِيْنَا الْجَزْلَ وَلَا تَحْكُمْ فِيْنَا بِالْعَدْلَ
"O son of Khattab(خطاب)! You are not giving us enough and you are not judging among us with justice.
"You are being oppressive and you are not giving us enough.
And you really need to look at the first statement, you are not giving us enough that’s what it really means.
And Umar(عُمَر) is oppressive because he is not giving him enough.
So, you know sometimes people their standard of justice is how good you are to them.
That is, they see the world, they are the centre of universe.
If you treat them well then you are the best, if you treat them bad, you are the worst.
Doesn’t really make a difference whether they have merits or not.
They judge according to how they are treated.
And this is a statement that is false, so Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) wanted to respond back.
Al-Hurr Bin Qais(الحر بن قيس) interrupted and he said, Allahعَزّوجَلّ has told Muhammad  ﷺ,
وَاَعْرِضْ عَنِ الْجَاهِلِيْنِ
"Stay away from the ignorant and this man is one of them."
He is saying that about his uncle, but Al-Hurr Bin Qais(الحر بن قيس) defends Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه
because he is defending the truth.
Even if that leads to him insulting his own uncle.
This man is among Al-Jahiliyeen(الجاهلين) and the Ayah(آية) says,
وَاَعْرِضْ عَنِ الْجَاهِلِيْنِ
stay away from them. Ibn Abbas(ابن عباس) said,
فَمَا تَجَاوَزَهَا حِيْنَ تَلَاهَا
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) didn’t go beyond that as soon as the verse was revealed.
فَاِنَّه’ كَانَ وَقَافًا عِنْدَ كِتَابِ الله
"Because Umar(عُمَر) was a person who would stop at the Book of Allah."
When he would hear a Ayah(آية) he would stop.
He would follow the rule of Allahعَزّوجَلّ he would not go ahead with what he intended
because now he heard a Naseeha(نصيحه) the Ayah(آية) of the Book of Allahعَزّوجَلّ telling him to ignore.
So, he ignored Oyaiyna Bin Hassan(عيينه بن حصن).
Lets move on to the  other section,
HIS LIFE WITH HIS FAMILY:
Rasool Allah ﷺ was in a gathering with the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم
and Rasool Allah ﷺ would use various instructional methods to deliver the message to the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
For example, sometimes he would draw a diagram on the sand,
sometimes he would ask a question,
sometimes he would make a statement like an oath to make them attentive, to what he's going to say
and the statements of Rasool Allah ﷺ were very short and concise, so that they could be remembered.
So, all of these show you the Hikmah(حكمة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ as a Teacher.
Once Rasool Allah ﷺ was with the Sahabah(صحابه), so he asked them a question.
He said: "Tell me what tree is similar to the Mo’min(مؤمن), to the believer?
" Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عُمَر) said; I was with the Sahabah(صحابه).
And the Sahabah(صحابه) got lost in the trees of the desert.
The Sahabah(صحابه), their minds tuned in to the desert and they started mentioning names of tree from the desert.
While the tree Rasool Allah ﷺ was referring to right to, was right around the corner.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was referring to An-Nakhla(النخلة), the palm tree.
Since, the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم went around mentioning one tree after another, none of them knew the answer.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them the answer. He said: It is An-Nakhla(النخلة), the palm tree.
Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عُمَر) he went back home and he told his father, O my father! I knew the answer.
Umar(عُمَر) told him, "why didn’t you answer it then?"
Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عُمَر) said: "Because I was the youngest in the gathering
and there were people like you and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر), so I was shy, embarrassed.
I didn’t feel it right to answer in their presence."
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) didn’t like that answer, and he said;
"It would have been better if you have answered
and I would rather, that have you answer that question Bikadhaa(بكذا) Wa-kadhaa(وكذاء),
this was a statement what they would say meaning,
"Whatever you could sacrifice, it would have been better for me, if you mentioned the answer then."
What Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is teaching his son Abdullah(عبدالله) is that you should have courage.
You should speak up, when you know the truth.
You shouldn’t just stay there quietly because you are shy,
because you don’t want to talk in front of the gathering
and this is very important message to deliver it to your children.
Don’t be shy, don’t be ashamed if you know the right answer, you know the truth, answer it.
So, he is teaching his son Abdullah(عبدالله) to have courage
and this is an important thing that we need to teach our children.
In fact, sometimes parents would teach their children fear, not courage, fear.
Stay away from trouble, don’t answer, don’t talk, don’t speak up, don’t go to the Masjid(مسجد), don’t do this, don’t do that.
You should tell them, that they should uphold the truth no matter what the consequences are.
You should stand up for what is right no matter what the consequences are.
Parents do not make your children grow up to be chicken.
You need to raise them up having the Ikhlaq(اخلاق) of Islam, courage, sacrifice.
Ibrahim عليه السّلام is telling his son I want to slaughter you?
What do you say? Because he was brought up by Ibrahim عليه السّلام, he said,
يَا أَبَتِ افْعَلْ مَا تُؤْمَرُ
O my father do what you are commanded to do.
He was ready, Ismailعليه السلام was ready to die for the sake of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) use to care for, the Akhirah(آخرة) benefit for his children.
When Hafsa(حفصه), her husband died.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) wanted her to marry the best.
So, he goes to Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان).
I want fathers, I want parents in general, fathers and mothers to think about this.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) goes to Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان)
and he tells him, my daughter Hafsa(حفصه), I am offering her to you in marriage.
This is no, no to parents today, you don’t go offering your daughter around.
You wait until somebody comes, and if nobody comes you have her sit at home, until she dies.
No Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) he wants the best for his daughter.
He is not thinking about shame, embarrassment and he doesn’t think about these things.
I want her benefit, I want what is good for her, so he goes to Uthman(عثمان) and he says;
"I am offering you my daughter in marriage".
Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) comes back to Umar(عُمَر) and says;
قَدْ بَدَلِيْ اَلَّا تَزَوَّجَ فِيْ يَوْمِ هَذَا اَوْ يَوْمِ هَذَا
I am not interested in marrying, at this particular time.
Umar(عُمَر) didn’t like that answer.
Obviously, but you cannot force him.
Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) turned him down, it's very difficult.
but Uthman(عثمان) wasn’t interested in getting married at that particular time.
So, then Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) he goes to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and he offers Hafsa(حفصه) to him.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابوبكر الصديق) did not respond back, he did not say, yes or no. He just left.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said; And I was even more upset with Abu Bakr(ابوبكر),
at least Uthman(عثمان) told me the answer.
He said, No!. Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) just ignored me.
So Umar Ibn Khattab(عمرإبن ألخطاب) was very angry with Abu Bakr(أبوبكر), very angry.
A short while later, Rasool Allah ﷺ asks for Hafsa(حفصه) and he marries her, Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله).
So, Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) comes back to Umar(عُمَر) and he said: "I think you were upset with me?
" Umar(عُمَر) said: "Yes".
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: The reason why I didn’t answer back is because I heard Rasool Allah ﷺ mention her name,
and I am not going to be the one, to expose the secret of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and if Rasool Allah ﷺ did not get marry to her, I would have married her.
Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) said; It was something I heard in private, and I wouldn't tell anybody about it.
Rasool Ullah mentioned her name, so I wanted to wait and see if Rasool Allah ﷺ would marry her.
And if he didn’t, I would have married her.
But Allahعَزّوجَلّ chose for her the best, Muhammadﷺ.
But the thing here is, we are talking about how he is dealing with his family.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is eager to get the best husband for his daughter
and he is willing to go and offer her.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was strict with his family members.
And when he was a Khalifah(خليفه), he wanted to make sure that there is no favoritism going on,
and he was very strict about it.
Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عُمَر) said; I purchased some camels that were very weak because of fever.
These camels were sick, so they became very weak, skinny
Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عُمَر) purchased them and then he took them to Al-Hima(الهِما).
Al-Hima(الهِما) is a guarded area that is open for all, it is a common pasture.
So, the land doesn’t belong to any particular person.
It is guarded and any Muslim can take their flock there to feed.
So, Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عُمَر) he took his camels to this Hima(الهِما) and they grew fat
and then Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عُمَر) took them to the market place to sell.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) he used to inspect the markets of Madina.
So, during one of his inspections tours, he sees these fat healthy camels.
He said, who did these belongs to?
They said; They belonged to Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عُمَر).
So, he calls Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عُمَر) and he said; O Abdullah(عبدالله) what is this?
Abdullah(عبدالله) said; These are some camels I bought, they were very skinny
and I took them to Hima(الهِما) and now I want to sell them.
Umar(عُمَر) said; Yes!. You took them to Hima(الهِما) and the Muslims over there said;
Move away let the camels of the son of Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين) eat and they would bring them water
and say take good care of the camels of the son of Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين), until they grew fat.
Sell these camels, you take your capital and every single Dinar(دينار), you made in profit goes back to the treasury.
Because Umar(عُمَر) said that, because you are the son of the Khalifah(خليفه),
the Muslims were giving you preferred treatment and that’s why your camels became fat.
So, he said, you take your capital the money that you have invested and don’t make money any money out of this.
Abdullah Ibn Umar رضي الله عنه, he made some money from the Ghanaem(غنائم) of the Jalolah(جوالاء) this was the battle in Iraq.
So, Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عُمَر) being one of the fighter in the army, he got portion of the spoils of war.
So, he brought it to Madina and he wanted to sell it.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said; "Yes". You going to sell it, you are going to make a lot of money off, of it.
Actually, it cost him 40,000 and he sold it for four hundred thousand (400,000), so he made a lot of money.
It was a very good deal.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattabرضي الله عنه said; O my son Abdullah(عبدالله)!
Would you sacrifice any thing for me, if you know that you are father is going to hellfire?
Abdullah(عبدالله) said; O my father! I would sacrifice anything for you, anything.
Umar(عُمَر) said, well this merchandise of yours, which you want to sell, the Muslims are going to say,
he is the Sahabi(صحابي) of Rasool Ullah and he is the son of Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين)
and he the most beloved of his sons to him and then Umar(عُمَر) said, and that is true.
Umar(عُمَر) was saying, that you are the most beloved of my children to me.
So, the Muslims are going to give you the best deal.
They are going to sell you with the lower prices and they will buy from you with the highest prices.
So, let me tell you my son, I am going to give you best profit a man of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) can make.
For every Dirham(درهم) that you have invested I am going to give you a Dirham(درهم).
So, after it was sold for four hundred thousand,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) gave Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عُمَر) Eighty Thousand(80,000)
all of the rest went to Bait-Ul-Maal(بيت المال), the treasury.
Now, this is a legitimate deal but Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was very sensitive,
very sensitive to the way, his son would be treated.
In fact Abdullah(عبدالله) and Ubaidillah Bin Umar(عبيدالله بن عمر) were in Iraq,
they were with Abu Musa Al-Asha’ari(ابوموسى العشعري)
and Abu Musa Al-Asha’ari(ابوموسى العشعري) is appointed as a Governor by Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين).
So Abu Musa(ابوموسى) told Abdullah(عبدالله) and Ubaidillah(عبيدالله ), he said;
I want to send some money to the Khalifah(خليفه).
I want to send some money to Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين).
However, I am going to give you this money, you buy some items from Iraq, using this money
and you can take it to Madina and sell it and give the money back to Umar(عُمَر) and you keep the profit.
So, you see the deal here?
So, Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عُمَر) took the money that belongs to Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين),
should go back to the treasury and they bought some items from Iraq,
they carried the items and they wanted to sell them in Madina.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) when he knew about this deal he said: No.
He said, all of the money goes to the treasury.
Abdullah(عبدالله) said, I stayed, quiet and Ubaidillah(عبيدالله) argued with my father.
He said; But my father, if we lost in this deal we would have guaranteed the return of the money.
So, how come now when we made money you want to take it away from us?
Because if this turned out to be a sour deal, we would have paid you money out of our pockets
because this was a trust given by Abu Musa(ابوموسى).
Umar(عُمَر) said; Give the money back.
So, one of the Sahabah(صحابه) was sitting there he argued on behalf of Abdullah(عبدالله) and Ubaidillah(عبيدالله) and he said,
O Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين) how about you give them half of the profit and you take half?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he remained silent, so that's what happened.
His son Asim(عاصم) was in Iraq and he came with some plates and jewelry, and
some items that he brought them from Iraq.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) called Mo’aiqeeb(موعيقيب) his servant and he said;
Mo’aiqeeb(موعيقيب) take everything you see with Asim(عاصم) and deposit it in the treasury.
Asim(عاصم) said: But it belongs to me. Umar(عُمَر) said: No! You went to Iraq and you asked them to give you this.
Asim(عاصم) said; But I asked my family.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told Mo'aiqeeb(موعيقيب) take it, and leave it in treasury, take it all.
And he Stripped Asim(عاصم) of all of the items that he brought with him from Iraq and he put it in the treasury.
Abu Musa Al-Asha’ari(ابوموسى العشعري) he came from Iraq and he gave the wife of Umar(عُمَر) a gift.
Small item, he gave to her as a gift to wife of Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين).
Umar(عُمَر) comes in and he sees this gift with his wife he said; where did you get it from?
She said; Abu Musa Al-Asha’ari(ابوموسى العشعري) gave it to me, as a gift.
Umar(عُمَر) picked up that item and he hit her on the head, he banged her on her head and he said;
and why are you getting gifts from Abu Musa(ابوموسى)?
And then he said; call Abu Musa(ابوموسى).
Abu Musa(ابوموسى) came in and he was breathing, because they had dragged him and he had to run he said;
لَا تَعْجَلْ عَلَيَّا يا امير المؤمنين
O Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين), Don’t hasten in your judgment against me.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told him, and who told you give my wife gifts?
He took that item and he hit Abu Musa(ابوموسى) on the head.
And he said: Take it back to Bait-Ul-Maal(بيت المال).
I want to make a comment here
Abu Musa Al-Asha’ari(ابوموسى العشعري) has no blood relations with whatsoever, with the wife of Umar(عُمَر).
They are foreign to each other, Non-Mahram(محرم) and Abu Musa(ابوموسى) is giving her a gift.
If that were the conduct of the Sahabah(صحابه) it shows you how tight they were?
Ya’ani(يعني) for somebody to come and give the wife of his friend a gift shows you how tight and close the relationship was.
And how close Abu Musa(ابوموسى) was to Umar(عُمَر) and how close Sahabah(صحابه) were, they were like one family.
Because, why would Abu Musa(ابوموسى) give the wife of Umar(عُمَر) a gift?
But it shows that they had extremely close, and loyal, and brotherly relationship
to the extent that Abu Musa(ابوموسى) can give the wife of Umar(عُمَر) a gift.
Now, Umar(عُمَر) did not agree with that because he felt that this is a preferred treatment
just because she is the wife of Umar(عُمَر) doesn't entitle her to get gifts.
Because as he sees it, as a conflict of interest.
He is the Khalifah(خليفه), he shouldn't be getting gifts.
Especially from someone who is appointed by him, as a Governor.
Money shouldn't be used in such a way, by the way its the money of Abu Musa Al-Ash'ari(أبوموسى ألعشعري)
and he gave it to the wife of umar(عمر) as a gift.
And Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was very strict with his wives,
he didn’t want them to intervene in the affairs of state.
Once he was writing a letter reprimanding one of his governors,
so the wife of Umar(عُمَر) came and she said: Why are you being so harsh on him?
He said: You stay quiet go and do your stitching and stay away from the affairs of government.
Sometimes, the comments of Umar(عُمَر) were bit harsh and rough, and
and I hope that sisters will still going to show up tomorrow.
and you are not going to say that we wouldn't accept such statements.
Ya’ni(يعني) Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he was disciplining his wives
and that was the way of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب),
he didn't want his women to involve in the affairs of government.
Rasool Allah ﷺ would seek the advice of his wives.
Like for example, with Umm Salamah(ام سلمه) in Sulah-Hudaybiya(صلح الحديبيه),
she was the one who gave him the Nasihaa(نصيحه) of
Rasool Allah ﷺ, going himself and shaving his head slaughtering his animals.
But Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) he didn’t want his women to involve in the affairs of state.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) received some money,
so Hafsa(حفصه), Umm-Ul-Mo’mineen(امهات المؤمنين) came to Umar(عُمَر) and said,
Don’t forget your relatives, you need to give to your relatives, you need to make, Sula-Tur-Rahem(صلحةالرحم)
you need to be kind to your kinship,
and she was telling him about your rights and duties towards your family - the clan of Bannu Udae(بنوعدي).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he stopped her and he said:
غَشَشْتِيْ أَبَاكِيْ، وَ نَصَحْتِيْ أَقَارِبِكْ
You have cheated your father by being nice and well to your family.
He said; This money belongs to the Muslims.
I would give my relatives from my own personal money not from the money that belongs to the Muslims.
So, he said; you cheated your father, meaning, you are not doing your father good by giving me this Naseeha(نصيحه),
even though you are benefiting your relatives.
So, he was very strict with his house hold.
Now, how would Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) treat the house hold of Rasool Allah ﷺ, Ahlul-Bait(اهل البيت).?
He used to take special care of Ummahatul-Mo’mineen(امهات المؤمنين),
he used to love Al-Hassan wal-Hussain(الحسن ولحسين), Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب), Al-Abbas(العباس) and his son Abdullah(عبدالله)
and he used to put them in a very high status.
When he would send money to the house hold of Rasool Allah ﷺ
he would give them, so much and incase there is any shortage,
the shortage would be in the share of his own daughter, Hafsa(حفصه)
that’s where the shortage would be.
In what he gives to Hafsa(حفصه) the wife of Rasool Allah ﷺ why?
Because she is his daughter.
Once he gave Zaynab Bint Jahash(زينب بنت جحش), so much money,
huge pile of coins, so when Zaynab(زينب) saw that she said;
"May Allah forgive Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين).
There are other wives of Rasool Allah ﷺ, who would do a better job in distributing this money.
" He told her, no, no , no this is not for distribution, this is yours.
She thought that, he is bringing her the money to distribute among the rest of Ummahatul-Mo’mineen(امهات المؤمنين)
but she was told that all of this is your portion.
She was so terrified, by the amount of it, she told her servants to cover it with a cloth.
It was so much for her.
And then she told her servants to put her hand under the cloth
and take out from it and go and give it to orphans, to widows, to Miskeen(مسكين) to the needy
and the pile was decreasing going down, going down going down, until her servant said:
"O Umm-Ul-Mo’mineen(امهات المؤمنين), Zaynab(زينب)! Why don’t you leave some for us? We have a right in it."
So, then Zaynab(زينب) said, alright take what is under that cloth.
They uncovered it and there were more than Eighty Dirham(درهم) left.
Zaynab(زينب) she was so, terrified with this amount of money, the whole concept of all of this wealth coming in.
You know, in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ they were so poor.
A month would pass by without ever having a hot meal.
Zaynab(زينب) raised her hands up and said: "O Allah!
Don’t allow me to live until, the next time Umar(عُمَر) gives me At'ta(عطاء)."
And she died soon after that.
She felt that this wealth is a Fitnah(فِتْنَه) I don’t want to see this again.
So O Allah! take me away before this happens.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ accepted her Dua(دُعَا) and she died.
She was the first of the wife of Rasool Allah ﷺ to pass away.
The wives of Rasool Allah ﷺ Ummahatul-Mo’mineen(امهات المؤمنين)
were urging Umar(عُمَر) to allow them to make Hajj(حَجْ) and he was refusing but when they insisted, he agreed.
And he told Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف) and Sa’ad Bin Abi Waqas(سعد بن ابي وقاص) to accompany them
and he said; One of you be in front and one of you should be in back and don’t walk with them.
Because they are non Mahram(محرم).
So, he said; Don’t walk with them.
You walk one ahead and one behind.
And he said; Whenever they spend the night you have them stay in a protected area and you stand and guard them.
And in Tawaf(طواف) do not allow any man to make Tawaf(طواف) with them, Only woman can make Tawaf(طواف) with them.
He was giving special care to Ummahatul-Mo’mineen(امهات المؤمنين).
Nobody would ever be prevented from Tawaf(طواف).
The only exception was when Ummahatul-Mo’mineen(امهات المؤمنين) are making Tawaf(طواف) no men are allowed there,
so only women can make Tawaf(طواف) with them.
These were exceptional rules that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) had for Ummahatul-Mo’mineen رضي الله عنهن.
And as I have said; he was very close to Ali(علي), he was one of his senior advisors,
and he used to love Al-Hassan wal Hussain(الحسن ولحسين).
Al-Hussain Ibn Ali(الحسين ابن علي) said and Al-Hussain(الحسين) was young, very young at that time,
he said; Umar(عُمَر) saw me once and he told me, O my son! Why don’t you visit me?
How come you are not visiting me?
So, Al-Hussain(الحسين) said; I will Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين).
Al-Hussain(الحسين) said: I went to visit Umar(عُمَر)
and he was having a private session with Muawiya Ibn Abi Sufiyan(معاويه ابن ابي سفيان).
And Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) was standing at the door and he wasn’t even giving permission to come in.
Even Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) wasn’t allowed to enter the room
- because Umar(عُمَر) was meeting privately with Muawiya(معاويه).
Al-Hussain(الحسين) said: When I saw Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) himself walking away,
I didn’t bother asking for permission to go in, so I left.
A while later Umar(عُمَر) meets me and he says, O my son! How come you didn’t visit me?
Al-Hussain(الحسين) said: Well I did visit you
but you were meeting with Muawiya(معاويه) and Abdullah(عبدالله) wasn’t even given the permission to go in,
so I didn’t ask for permission.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: O my son!
I would give you priority over my own son, Abdullah(عبدالله) because you are in my head.
Umar(عُمَر) placed his hand on the head of Al-Hussain(الحسين) and he said; It is Allah and then you.
For me, it is Allah and then you.
That was the love that he had to Al-Hussain(الحسين) and Al-Hassan(الحسن) the sons of Ali Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنه.
Al-Abbas(العباس) and Ali Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنهم had a financial dispute Ali(علي) and his uncle Abbas(العباس).
So, they came in to meet with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) and Umar(عُمَر) had Abdur Rahman Ibn Awf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف),
Az-Zubair Bin Al-Awam(الزبير بن عوام), Sa’ad bin Abi Waqas(سعد بن ابي وقاص), some other Sahabah(صحابه), Uthman(عثمان).
So, Uthman(عثمان) said; O Ameer-Ul-Mo’mineen(امير المؤمنين) why don’t you judge between these two men and get it over with.
The dispute has been going on for some time.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said; Slow down,
Didn’t you know that Rasool Allah ﷺ said that the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) do not leave behind any inheritance.
إِنَّا مَعْشَرَ الْأَنْبِيَاءِ لَا نُوْرَثْ مَا تَرَكْنَاه’ صَدَقَهْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says that we the prophets do not leave behind inheritance.
What we leave behind is charity, is Sadaqah(صدقه).
So, this is an exception from the rule of inheritance.
Inheritance usually goes to the family members but the exception are with the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء).
They said; Yes! Umar(عُمَر) asked Ali(علي) and Abbas(عباس), he said: Don't you know that Rasool Allah ﷺ  said that?
They said: Yes!."
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: And you know that Rasool Allah ﷺ in his days, he used to live off the Fai(فيئ),
the spoils of war that came from Bannu Nadhir(بنو نضير).
What he used to do is he use to take from it, enough to support his family for a year
and then the rest would give it out in Sadaqah(صدقه), isn’t that true?
They said; Yes!, that’s true.
Umar(عُمَر) said; And when Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away, Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) held on to that land
and he would give you enough for a year and he would spend the rest in Sadaqah(صدقه), isn’t that true?
Ali(علي) and Abbas(عباس) said; "Yes!".
Umar(عُمَر) said: And then when I became Khalifah(خليفه) for the first two years of my life that's was what I was doing.
I would take what Rasool Allah ﷺ used to take and would give it to you, Ali(علي) your portion goes to your wife Fatima(فاطمه)
because she is daughter of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and Al-Abbas(العباس), because you were asking for your portion from Muhammadﷺ being his uncle
and I used to give you that isn’t that true?
They said: Yes!.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: And then I gave it to you because you asked me for it.
And you said, that you will follow the same way that I was following,
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was following and Rasool Allah ﷺ was following in distributing the harvest of this land
and you agreed to that and you took it from me.
And now you are coming and complaining that you are having a dispute among you.
I am not going to make any ruling among you.
You either follow the same way or you give it back to me and I will take care of it.
So, when it came to following the rules, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) would follow the rules strictly,
and even though he had the love of the house hold of Rasool Allah ﷺ but in this particular situation,
he told Al-Abbas(العباس) and Ali(علي) either you are up to it,
and you can take care of that land yourself and not fight among you
or you give it back to me and I will be the one to manage it.
Tayeb(طيب),
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا
IT SHUDDERS IN PAIN FREELY
MY CHASITY, MY MODESTY!
OH MUSLIM, YOU SAW
MY INJURY AND THE INJURY OF MY PRIDE